Guide to the Carl and Helen Winter Papers TAM 583
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
Carl and Helen Winter Papers
circa 1890-circa 2002
TAM 583
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
8.75 linear feet (10 boxes)
Carl Winter (1906-1991) and Helen Winter (1908-2001) were Communist Party USA activists and officials. Carl Winter was the Chair of the Communist Party of Michigan, was convicted in 1949 under the Smith Act of conspiracy to overthrow the government of the U.S. and served five years in prison, later became the editor of the Party's newspaper, The Worker. His wife Helen was herself a Smith Act defendant and daughter of Alfred Wagenknecht (1881-1956), a leading member of the Socialist Party, and later a charter member of Communist Party USA. The collection contains correspondence, including Carl Winter's prison correspondence, family correspondence including that of Alfred Wagenknecht with his wife Hortense and daughter; some documentation of the politiccal activity of Wagenknecht; clippings, most related to Carl Winter's Smith Act trial, and to the Winters' Michigan activism; Detroit Police Departments Red Squad files on Carl and Helen Winter; FBI files; speeches; Communist Party of Michigan printed ephemera; Allison family materials (the maternal branch of Helen's family); speeches, writings; interview transcripts; commemorative and memorial materials and memorabilia. See also the more detailed descriptions of the contents of each box.
Winter, Carl, 1906-1991
Historical/Biographical Note
Carl Winter (1906-1991) and Helen Winter (1908-2001) were Communist Party USA activists and officials. Carl Winter was the Chair of the Communist Party of Michigan, was convicted in 1949 under the Smith Act of conspiracy to overthrow the government of the U.S. and served five years in prison, later became the editor of the Party's newspaper, The Worker. His wife Helen was herself a Smith Act defendant and daughter of Alfred Wagenknecht (1881-1956), a leading member of the Socialist Party, and later a charter member of Communist Party USA. the Communist Party USA.
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains correspondence, including Carl Winter's prison correspondence, family correspondence including that of Alfred Wagenknecht with his wife (Wagenknecht separated from his wife Hortense in 1930 and was finally divorced in January of 1948) and daughter; some documentation of the politiccal activity of Wagenknecht (he traveled to the Soviet Union on several occasions, served as the Executive Secretary of the National Committee to Aid Victims of German Fascism, and was the State Chairman of the Communist Party in Missouri from 1938 to 1941 and in Illinois from 1941 to 1945); clippings, most related to Carl Winter's Smith Act trial, and to the Winters' Michigan activism; Detroit Police Departments Red Squad files on Carl and Helen Winter; FBI files; speeches; Communist Party of Michigan printed ephemera; Allison family materials (the maternal branch of Helen's family); speeches, writings; interview transcripts; commemorative and memorial materials and memorabilia. See also the more detailed descriptions of the contents of each box.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Separated Materials
Photographs separated from the collection to PHOTOS 286, including photographs and negatives from Alfred Wagenknecht's trip to China, photographs and negatives from Alfred Wagenknecht's trip in 1922 to London and Germany, a disbound scrapbook of Wagenknecht-Allison family photographs circa 1910-1930, photographs of Helen and Carl Winter from Communist Party events, photographs of labor activists and Communists including Carl and Helen Winter, Gus Hall, and Elizabeth Gurley Flynn, portraits of Alfred Wagenknecht, photographs from Winter's trips to Mongolia, East Germany, and other Soviet Bloc countries, photographs of Communist Party members like Elizabeth Gurley Flynn and Gus Hall, and photographs from the Mosley Demonstration (1948).
Communist Party of the United States of America (Mich.).; Wagenknecht, Alfred; Winter, Carl, 1906-1991; Winter, Helen, 1908-2001; Communism |z Michigan; Communist trials |z United States.; Communists |z United States
- Papers, 1945-1972, undated (Box 1)
  General note
  The bulk of this box consists of the Detroit Police Departments Red Squad files on Carl and Helen Winter, beginning when they moved to Detroit in 1945, and ending in 1972. The files are proceded by a folder containing a photocopy of an approximately 25 pp. chronology of their activities, originally recorded on 4x6 index cards. There are also several folders of Carl Winter's letters to Helen from prison, 1952-1955, as well as some correspondence with attorney John Abt. There is also a "Unique Contribution Award" to the Winters from the CPUSA, dated 8/13/1987. The box also contains memos on Communist Party USA functions in Michigan.
- Papers, circa 1950-circa 1965 (Box 2)
  The majority of the contents are loose, fragile newspaper clippings, most related to Carl Winter's Smith Act trial, and to Communist political activity in Michigan. There are also a brief and memorandum from the trial of Saul Lawrence Wellman, Nathan Kaplan aka Nat Ganely, Thomas De Witt Dennis Jr., Philip Schatz, Helen Mary Winter, and William Allen, Applicants, vs. United States of America, Appellee (District Court of the US for the Eastern District of Michigan); a file of Smith Act related "defense" work. There is also a compilation of the political activities of Helen Winter, 1945-1948, apparently distilled from a larger government report[s] of unknown provenance, but possibly based in part on information supplied by John Lautner.
- Papers, 1937-2001 (Box 3)
  Contains Communist Party of Michigan fliers, leaflets and other printed ephemera, memoranda; speeches by the Winters principally relating to the Smith Act, other anti-communism, and civil liberties; correspondence mostly related to Carl Winter's Smith Act trial including a letter from Helen Winter to Elizabeth Gurley Flynn; congratulatory letters to Helen Winter on her 85th birthday, condolences and other materials from memorial events for Carl and Helen Winter; several folders of previously loose printed ephemera relating to the Communist movement and to anti-communism; documents from the Colombia Communist Party XI Congress in 1971, and the Detriot Urban League.
- Papers, 1943-2006 (Box 4)
  Contains papers from the Communist Party USA convention in 1991, papers from Carl Winter's second Federal indictment regarding his Party membership in 1955, memorial programs for civil rights activists and communist party members, writings and poetry by members of the Allison family (Helen's maternal family), Communist Party of Michigan printed ephemera, a transcript of a TV Interview with Gus Hall in 1974, articles on Communism and the Smith Act and other anti-communist laws by Carl and Helen Winter, files on Murio Eduardo Machado, a Communist party member from Venezuela, birthday tribute papers to Helen Winter, an audio cassette recording from Carl Winter's memorial service, and obituaries and condolences; and printed materials by and about the World and U.S. Peace Councils, the National Negro Labor Council, and Paul Robeson.
- Papers, 1907-2000 (Box 5)
  Contains mostly Allison family papers (Helen Winter's maternal family), including correspondence, compilations of genealogies, poetry and other writings, and obituaries; transcripts of separate interviews with Carl and Helen Winter; biographical interview transcripts; correspondence from Helen Winter's trips to foreign conferences. The box also contains articles for the Reference Center for Marxist Studies by Helen Winter, and notes from the Communist Party USA Convention in 1976. The box also contains a plaque from the Detriot Urban League to Carl Winter.
- Papers, 1943-2006 (Box 6)
  Contains mostly Carl Winter's letters to Helen Winter and family from prison, 1952-1955, and hate mail sent to the Winters. Also contains Hortense Allison and Alfred Wagenknecht (parents of Helen Winter)'s obituaries and condolence letters, and Helen Winter's World Peace Council notes and printed ephemera. Also contains material on the Smith Act arrests in Michigan, including printed ephemera, fundraising materials, fliers, circulars, and clippings. Court transcripts of the Eugene Dennis et al. v. USA court case are also included.
- Papers, 1948-1955 (Box 7)
  Mostly contains correspondence between Helen and Carl Winter, Carl Winter and Sam Weissenberg (Carl's father), Ernest Goodman and Winter, and Winter and his lawyers while he was in prison (1952-1955). Also contains indictment and parole materials for Carl Winter, World and U.S. Council for Peace printed ephemera, Victims of the Smith Act and related fliers, fundraising materials, and other printed ephemera, clippings from Spotlight (Committee to Keep McCarthyism Out o Michigan by Fighting Smith Act Persecutions) and the Labor Defender (Civil Rights Congress of Michigan) on the Smith Act, and amnesty requests to Truman regarding the Smith Act victims.
- Papers, 1932-2004 (Box 8)
  Contains Carl Winter's prison records, Michele Stone's (the daughter of Helen and Carl Winter) FBI files, correspondence between Carl Winter and Michele Stone while he was in prison (1952-1955), Carl Winter's lecture notes on the Soviet Union and socialism, political economy, and trade unions, an undated typescript of "A Dialogue between Gordon, an American Lawyer, and Petrovich, a Soviet Lawyer, at Moscow" by Ernest Goodman, and Communist Party Michigan materials including a history of the Michigan Party, pamphlets, circulars, and other writings for the Communist Party by Carl Winter. Other materials include clippings from the Jewish press on the Communist Party in the USA and the Smith Act, and printed ephemera and fliers of the National Negro Labor Council and Progressive Youth Organizing committee.
- Papers, 1924-1926 (Box 9)
  Contains Alfred Wagenknecht's correspondence with his wife Hortense Allison and a small amount of correspondence with other family members, including Helen Winter (his daughter), condolences upon his death and a program and other material from a memorial service. The letters (1925-1926) are mostly personal and concern Hortense's health, but Wagenknecht wrote about Communist party meetings and labor movements including his work for the General Relief Committee Textile Strikers. The box also contains personal items belonging to Wagenknecht, including his passport and his membership cards to the Workers and Socialist Parties.
- Papers (Box 10)
  Contains the oversized high school diplomas of Carl and Helen Winter.